So.
Hi, everybody.
Welcome back. Um, welcome to the means.
This advanced programming course class I
hope we hope with that you enjoy the show
and being an experiment isn't too painful
so far.
Yes, sorry, I do turn on.
And now there is the final step.
Uh, which is, uh, as promised the uh.
They will sample few of the text of the
projects, of course AI generated.
Um.
I mean the way we we generated the the
the text it's interesting basically I
explained the the three examples we
discussed together and then I said OK
these were the examples in classes you
know.
Course, et cetera.
And there are basically three types of
projects, Explorer codebase,
Explorer language feature or similar and
generally code.
And then we started this.
So actually I I also tested trying to get
the generation done on my behalf,
but the AI.
Start too much from the,
but actually one of the goal with this
project is that you explore something
that you for sure not don't know.
So in some cases I even pick up things
that I know.
But I'm not an expert.
Because one of the thing that I think the
AI is crucial is the fact that.
It allows you,
if you know the proper questions,
to learn very fast a new technology, OK?
And so it's part of the game asking to
investigate through the AI something you
don't know.
Because you don't know the specifics,
but you know a lot of things that we
covered within the course,
and so you must be able to pose the
proper questions so that you can you can
get useful answers.
And also when you read the output,
you should be able to parse the output
and make yourself an opinion whether the
output is correct or not. OK,
so as promised.
The final project that we will of course
review the the projects and it will be
possibly be who you you will get a grade
of course.
But actually you will receive the as a
feedback of how complete well done as
recognize the work you put into this
project.
But then when you will come to the oral
exam and the big important announcement,
we will of course we will try to set up a
a a slot, a sets of slots.
For an agenda so that you can book for
your exam,
but we we decided we're not too bound to
the dates in the calendar. OK,
so don't worry if you are in,
we will set up a number of slots.
We assume one hour slot.
OK.
So be prepared to talk to him and fill up
an hour and and of course among the
discussion there will be a possible end
point can be your your project. OK,
so and.
That is the I think I expect that you
were expecting something. OK, so.
Having said that.
Let's see, I mean,
I mean in between one it.
So the format of the project that will be
posted by tonight inside the I would say.
Either I I I don't decide it yet how to
support this,
but probably either in the final section
or I will post the comment in the channel.
So far there will be about 30 projects
and for each time.
I don't see particular problems in if two
of you decide.
Independently to have the same project,
but I I don't even,
I don't think either encourage it. OK,
I mean if you if you're able to do
different projects,
I think it will be a nice thing.
You can, if you like,
discussions about your ideas, et cetera.
By the way, if you're working on.
Even more interesting exchange of ideas
and.
As you may see,
the format is the following so.
Internal memory management in GCC during
correlation,
which is a super interesting topic.
Uh.
Analyze how GCC manage memory internally
during the compilation process,
focusing on its allocation strategies
region based.
Memory pools,
garbage collection like mechanism and how
this contribute to performance modularity
and correctness within the compiler
pipeline.
And basically.
All the project have this structure with
free free tasks,
so in this case explain the internal
memory management model.
Uh.
And how different compiler subsystem from
10 middle in the land and optimizer use
these memory facilities.
So this is a rather broad exploration of
the GCC code base.
Analyze relevant GCC source code and
documentation to illustrate concrete
example of how memory is allocated,
reused or discarded during parsing.
Gimple RTL generation,
which is the intermediate representation
which is used by GCC and optimization
passes highlight trade-offs and rationale
behind GCC's design choices.
Document the prompts using VDI and
describe how you will find your finding.
I mean and the third task basically is
the same for all the projects,
which is the thing that we discussed so.
Uh, producer,
in this case a document as detailed as
you think it.
It can be given the time you you have and.
The the target generation can be
technical,
so you can easily spend one one page
around the a part of a of a code that you
find interesting and explaining why and.
By saying that this should be AI
generated, it doesn't mean that,
as we already commented,
that must be a single shot generation.
It can be a set of generation.
You can use the canvas.
Uh,
for those AI which support the canvas
that allows you in place editing. Uh,
so I mean it's not uh.
I I can't touch the text or the image is
generated.
I mean it's suppose you you want to cheat
into an exam that is asking for this
output and you have to produce the output
to sustain the exam.
In this case it's not cheating because
it's the require requirements to.
For for the course, OK,
but if you spend your time to get a nice
document,
at some point you may even share it on
the on on the Internet or someone else be
interest. I mean so.
Spend well your time.
OK, um.
O.
Category A as a promise and category A is
the name that we discussed it with the I
it's I mean it doesn't mean nothing.
It is is about investigation.
Of the implementation,
another interesting investigation can be
the C group's implementation in the Linux
kernel.
This is this one is for those of you that
are passionate about system Linux system,
operating system, kernels and stuff.
It's interesting because the how control
groups are implemented inside the Linux
kernel focusing on the internal
architecture, data structure,
integration with process management and
resource controllers.
And it's interesting because the kernel
typically is super optimized in the way
memory is allocated and and managed and
and and how ownership is managed and how
pools gets used.
So it's an interesting exploration.
That is really to understand how the
operation on C groups are implemented
really for containers.
OK,
let's take some a couple of cogeneration.
So.
For code generation,
I try to include the number of
applications that are.
Some of them are around the programming
language space.
Generate the parser,
generate the interpreter,
these kind of things,
and others more oriented if someone some
of you are interested in graphics,
etcetera.
The very first one is to generate the.
Um, very bad. Uh.
3D library and then use the library to
implement some 3D something.
OK as an example or in this case
implement A multi-threaded Mandelbrot
viewer with the the ability of zoom
export and path animation which is record.
A browsing inside the the the fractal and
then you get a video out of it.
Uh, there is uh.
A face detector web application which you
run inside the the on the client side and
so there are interesting aspects.
To deal with.
And there are.
The request to implement some library,
in this case a 2D game engine.
Which is another nice task,
a better one than we use the for Arcanoid
in particular. No events, no timers,
a true game loop.
Featuring a manual game loop without
using timer controls. OK, so that's.
Uh.
Some binary disassembly.
So in particular something that is
capable of decoding into text web
assembly.
Hmm.
Something revolving around the AI.
This one is nice is implementing an MCP
server which expose a directory of CVS
files as a data source knowledge for the
AI. So if someone some of you.
Is interested about, you know,
MCB protocol and AI integration with
knowledge bases, etcetera.
This can be interesting.
Some good old XML parsing.
Um.
For those that are more mathematical of
you,
I thought they would be nice to implement
a transpiler that implements a domain
specific language for statistical
computation and sample sequences that is
rewritten into JavaScript.
Of course, I mean for it. Well,
let let's go through the the list and
then I will give some remarks about this
parser interpreter for the Shakespeare
programming language.
You know Shakespeare.
That's part of the assignment,
learning about something.
Shakespeare is one among several.
It's likewise space.
It's a fun programming language.
Shakespeare was designed so that
Shakespeare programs can be read as poems.
That was, but it's for fun. I mean,
it's basically,
I could have said they implemented a
basic interpreter and would have been the
same, but Shakespeare is fun.
Um, let's have a look at the Uh.
The last type,
so I mean explored language feature or
libraries or something revolving around
that.
So for instance,
understands Haskell's notion of kinds and
investigate to what extent similar ideas
exist or can be emulated in F# and
JavaScript.
I mean we all the programming languages
are two equivalent. OK,
so I mean for sure it can be expressed.
Many of the construct that we discussed
during the course is are basically
designed.
To make programming languages more
expressive,
which means that we can express with less
text, more semantic,
possibly in a composable way.
So that you can compose the feature of
your programming language and this lets
you to the ability to express with very
little text significant amount portions
of a program or or of an algorithm and so
this kind.
Of assignments basically meant to have
you think.
About the fact that if something is
unavailable in a programming language,
this doesn't mean that it can't be
implemented.
To some extent you can implement your own
library, which approximates somehow.
The same feature.
Sometimes you may have to meet a program.
I mean sometimes you may think, OK,
you know I use the the the preprocessor
in C++.
Uh,
so that I macro expand and I introduce
some uh uh.
Some macros that allows me to to express
constructs that are not present in the
language,
leveraging on the fact that during the
compilation text would be program text
would be rewritten using the macro.
Uh, expansion system. So uh.
In general, as you may notice,
all these tracks are very, very broad.
I mean every one of these can produce
dozens of different projects speaking
about different things and perfectly
compatible with this specification. OK,
so this is for to encourage you to define.
Yourself and follow your personal
interest during the project. OK,
so if you feel more attracted about type
generation, OK,
you wanna play with meta programming?
Let's do that there are angles in which
you can take the the the and approach the
problem which are exactly acceptable.
If you have any doubt,
write to me and and Professor Kurdi.
To me,
please write me on teams and you you you
first say advanced programming and then
so that I know that you are you are in
need of assistance because.
I crossed the 200,
000 unread e-mail in my inbox.
Even if I go and roll the dice likeliness
that I bump into yours, it's small.
I I don't know how to manage this so.
So for programming language features,
I try to range from more foundational
like the kinds in Askell to.
The type system which makes possible
language integration integrated query in
C# because the type algebra which lies
behind the the link technology.
In in.net is quite interesting,
so including because some things are
explicitly mentioned and others less so a
feature which is interesting and deeply.
Integrated with the link is are the
extension methods.
Extension methods are a way in C# to add
extra methods to classes that are already
compiled and to which you don't have even
access to.
It's another form of syntactic sugar that
has been introduced in the language,
which is interesting.
Um.
And the.
And then uh.
Few example around how the link
expression can be compiled to object
browsing and SQL so that you can see both
browsing of in memory programming
language structures and cogeneration for
SQL.
So if you're passionate about databases
and and data management and type systems,
this is a nice one. Duck typing.
Duck typing is a.
It's not popular anymore,
but the 10 years ago,
I mean actually it made the fortune of
Python, unfortunately.
It's it's a philosophy basically that
typing and it's interesting.
To observe how the typing can be obtained
in different rogramming languages if.
So JavaScript, Python, I mean Python.
Yeah,
it is known for that Java and C# and and
those were sherry picket because the
answer, especially for the last two.
May be really interesting.
So that that one, uh,
gives you a lot of uh.
Angles too.
You like parametric polymorphism and C++
in Java and C# at the end of the 90s were
all the rage for parametric polymorphism,
which we all.
Give it for granted by now,
but back then it was a super cool feature
and and they have a three very different
implementation of the same thing and one
of the three C++ it's even.
Turing complete at compile time,
so you may induce the compiler to execute
code on your behalf in the in in the
journey to resolve the.
Uh,
some types and and there are few core
reasons because of this.
So basically this revolves around the.
Finding why you can't have a Java
template metaprogramming or C# template
metaprogramming only C++ template
metaprogramming.
And the answer is interesting.
Um.
I resorted also to all languages. Still,
if you're in love of good old programming
languages that made history,
Smalltalk and Clos are clearly
interesting Smalltalk.
Is considered the father of object
oriented programming and CLOS was the
common Lisp object system which was which
introduced a number of features.
Mostly bound to Lisp and you have to
compare with more modernjavaand.
net approach types.
Um.
I attempted also to have some web stuff.
I know that in the audience there are
people interested in web technologies,
so there are a lot of look how Chromium
Chrome is implemented.
On the end, in this case,
Angular JS versus React versus jQuery,
of course. I mean,
I'm not looking for the implementation of
that. I I don't care. I mean,
I don't give you. It's interesting.
From an advanced programming perspective
to look the differences between the three.
In particular,
I mentioned the three because React has a
very peculiar implementation of its
internal working.
And it's radically and totally different
than jQuery.
And the same can be said around Angular
and async programming that we discussed
it and why it is important because
basically React and Angular works mostly
because of Ajax, I mean and the design is.
Deep even in jQuery too.
I mean all three frameworks,
all the web single application page
frameworks basically give you have a
relevant role in terms of async,
which means promises and the thing we
said and we discussed so.
Always remember that we are interested in
reading the advanced programming
perspective. I mean,
so I'm not interested in receiving a
manual that tells me how to do our React
application. I'm interested in, OK, look,
this feature is very nice in Reactor
because.
Reactor is manipulating the DOM in this
way and generates code,
so it's a code generator in that way so
that you get this effect.
Look at how nice is the data structure.
Dictionaries in JavaScript are
implemented this way and so on. OK,
so focus on the advanced programming
features that have been used and all the
example that I tried to pick up.
Are basically interesting in the way the
feature features features of the various
programming languages have been adopted
and used I have.
Quotation and quasi quotation in
programming languages.
We touched the subject,
but this is an opportunity to learn more
of a very important notation asking to
compare lisp you don't you you know
little about.
And PHP you may know something about and
ASP you don't know anything about because
it's in the past now. Nevertheless,
they are more related than you might
think.
And so, uh,
it's an interesting exploration.
Um.
Lexical closures, lexical closures,
if you,
I mean we learn that lexical closure is
fundamental. It's an essential element,
for instance,
in continuation passing style.
And so it's important to understand
whether a programming language implements
or not and how implements.
Lexical closures,
because it may be it may seem trivial,
but it's not.
Not all lexical closure implementation
are equivalent. There may be restrictions.
In the way a language supports the
features,
so I mean it's interesting to look into
the details.
So in this case I picked up.
Spoiler Python, for instance,
in the beginning was not properly
implementing lexical closures.
If you look,
you will learn that at some point they
fixed the language, but in the.
Original version of Python.
Python wasn't supporting lexical, so Lua,
Python, JavaScript and Perl.
A big boy from the 90s that is basic.
I mean, how many of you know about Pearl?
But you you write coding per now. OK,
you know that there is a Perl programming
language. OK, Perl was a.
Strange and interesting and audible
programming,
but actually it signed history because
regular expressions,
all the regular expression available in
basically all programming languages today
are in after the current implementation.
So Perl did change the world and we all
use the Perl regex in any other
programming language.
OK and as you can see.
Typescript and JavaScript and dynamic
typing.
There are some that are more.
So for instance,
if you are a programming language
passionate that would like to learn about
the subtle things inside the programming
language, this can be, for instance,
an interesting project.
Because uh.
Um, JavaScript,
we said as no type constructors.
Uh, and it it has dynamic typing.
I mean a variable can change uh the type
uh is bound to during the course during
the execution.
Um,
TypeScript tries to support the type
system with type constructors.
Similar to Java or C# or less,
but also with dynamic typing and static
typing.
Now dynamic typing and static typing are
not so easy to be mixed together.
There are only two successful
implementations.
With that I know of as of today,
one is Visual Basic.
Visual Basic did support this thing and
the other is TypeScript.
So it's interesting because when you
allow both static typing and dynamic
typing then you need rules.
That allows you to discriminate,
decide when you stop type checking.
I mean there are a little bit implication.
OK.
Let me see if there there is some. Uh,
I basically.
Oh,
this is another interesting one for a um
programming a language passionate.
Um.
To study. In this case, for instance,
you can search and you will find also
scientific papers around the the F sharp
units of measure that you may find it
useful to read.
And the paper from Andrew Kennedy in in
this case can be used for instance to
cross check your output instead of asking
to the I Are you sure?
And uh, this is, uh,
an interesting it's it's another.
Very interesting aspect of programming
language design because touching in a
programming language a notion which is a
numeric type,
which is so core and then blending the.
Unit of measure which is not just a tag
because the language supports the
dimensional computation.
So if you divide the meter per seconds
you you get a new measure which is meter
per second.
And so in this respect,
it's not just tagging things around,
it's more than that.
It's interesting to to to understand how
it is possible to statically type check
the whole thing.
And eventually get a code which has no
trace at runtime of all this work,
which is clearly useful.
Uh to avoid I there is also uh CC plus
plus in rust. When I ask the comparison,
I always try to mix different things.
I mean C++.
Very fast, very complicated,
three key programming language. C,
very clean, very old,
very basic and Rust the attempt to
produce a better C with with the memory
management and with the borrowing and the
whole thing.
And in this case clearly the point is how
you compare the three and pros and cons
limits and there are.
A lot of angles that can be taken because.
Smart pointers, for instance,
are available both in Rust and in C++.
How the smart pointers implementation do
they differ?
Knock and so on.
OK, this is the 3D rendering,
so I guess we will pause more in the in
the.
In in the in the channel,
actually I was thinking that probably a
sensible way to move forward in this
respect is I created the assignment
channel in the team.
I post each assignment as a poster and if
you are interested in making that
assignment,
you comment the post saying I'm going to
do this.
I think it so that we we keep track of uh
what uh is doing uh.
Who is going doing what and we will keep
posting new projects.
One of you just wrote to me Andrea asking
for feedback that it will come.
Around the as a project,
as a project proposal and so you will
receive the answer shortly and that's it.
Questions.
So.
Let's say that we will share the link to
an agenda where you simply pick up the
slot and the submission of the project
should be.
A week, the week before, one week,
one week before. OK,
so basically you you apply for the
January the 10th.
So by January the 3rd you should have
submitted the the assignment so that we
have time for review.
You.
Oh, submission. No, no,
I think I will post a form.
Uh, so that I mean I I tried not to.
The name is.
No, exactly. But in general, no,
it's it's a e-mail.
I think it's should be just deleted. No,
I mean there will be a form that we post
on again in the in the.
In the in the team so that we got the
hour recorded by the system etcetera.
So everything is tracked.
You can Anna will ask to upload the.
At most 3 documents,
so various formats I will allow also zip.
If if there is, if it's too big,
I will also have a a field with the link
so that you can paste the share to
OneDrive so that we sure that in in in
some case in any case we can.
Get the information.
That's it.
Other questions, Sir.
OK, so.
Um.
Have a wonderful Christmas.
If you go home, have a safe trip home.
Talk to you at the exam. Don't be.
I mean study. Yes,
study to understand and learn the
advanced programming language features.
Uh, learn to be.
One of the things that I'm not sure,
at least for me,
I've been able to really ask you during
the classes is how subtle is program
advanced programming.
People that thinks that advanced
programming is.
The big super complicated notion,
but the reality is that under really
understanding the programming languages
is really understand the deep.
Interwined story between the syntax,
the semantics of every feature,
and how these interact with other
features so that you can get figures that
allows you to represent ideas.
And and and it's complicated and what it
makes makes it complicated is to
understand all the interactions that you
find from scoping rules, typing rules,
runtime implementation,
runtime type checking, static type.
Checking it and so on.
I mean it's a it's a sort of melody and
lots of things that some in some case
like Python probably Cacophony.
Sorry Python.
But basically, in any way,
I I hope that we we at least a little bit
show you all the ingredients,
but actually it's up to you to start
looking into a program and try to
appreciate the subtle things.
Not the big ones.
The big ones are the easy and simple one
and I tried in the we tried in this
assignments to try to capture this.
I mean C++ template meta programming why
it is really too incomplete.
There is exactly 1 feature that makes it
very incomplete,
otherwise without it it won't be.
So it's and why it's not in Java.
So think, think, think.
And I mean because it's about the
beautiful of programming languages. OK,
thank you and see you next year.
Next year, I mean.
Uh.
Next year in the sense at the exam,
but not OK, it wasn't.
Uh,
any any uh question from uh oh will uh um.
Lorenzo, OK,
will our code be reviewed by you or by AI?
By both?
I mean in the total coherence with the
course.
So I just showed that that the text has
been basically generated,
but it's not entirely true, so.
In in full transparency,
if you look at the at the chat, uh.
These were the proposals made it by the I
that in my personal opinion were simply
unacceptable.
So I retain the category system that the
I proposed and it's OK and as you can see
here there was another attempt and and.
It was three page description for the
assignment, so I decided no,
that's not OK and after a little bit of
struggle now category C and comparison of
lexical closure implementation in Lua,
Python, JavaScript, and I got.
Yes. OK. So yes, we will.
We may help us with with the eye,
but we will review the code because
accountability applies also to us,
not only to you.
OK.
Oh, and if you generate code,
the code should run.
OK.
If you provide a docker, we'll be fine.
I'm I'm pretty sure you those of you that
decide to generate code,
I'm pretty sure you will find a way to
give us a running version.
And in English.